

DATA SCIENCE PRACTICE LEAD & AD HINCT PROFESSOR OF DATA SCIENCE

1400 Maryland Ave. Havertown, PA 19083

□ (410) 231-9371 | ■ jacob.rozran@gmail.com | ♠ jakelearnsdatascience.com | ᡚjrozra200 | ் jacob-rozran | ♥ StatsManPHL

Summary_

In addition to being a leader, dad, uncle, & data guy, I am a data & technology professional with real-world experience in data science, data analytics, data engineering, fraud detection, risk modeling, building and maintaining data teams, project management, sales, consulting, and teaching.

My passion for data and statistics has inspired me to become an Adjunct Professor of Data Science & Statistics, which has improved my ability to explain complex subjects to all levels of understanding. I love to learn in general and am a data fanatic.

Data Science Skills

METHODS	APPLICATIONS	LANGUAGES	DATABASES
Data Visualization	RStudio	SQL	PostgreSQL
Hypothesis Testing	Jupyter Notebooks	R	Hive/Impala (Hadoop)
Project Management	Tableau/Metabase/Redash	Python	Athena (AWS)
Statistical Modeling	GitHub	Bash	MongoDB
Fraud Detection	Excel	Java Script	Neo4J

Experience

CivicActionsLafayette, CA

DATA SCIENCE PRACTICE LEAD

Feb 2021 - Present

- Building a Data Science Practice Area with > \$1MM revenue after 6 months; focused on data analysis, data science, people management, sales, marketing, and project management.
- For the Centers of Medicare and Medicaid (CMS), leveraging Natural Language Processing (NLP) in the creation and evaluation of System Security Plans (SSPs) to optimize the Authority to Operate (ATO) process; analyzing AWS usage to forecast annual usage and identify inefficiencies; using graph analysis and NLP to identify related documents to provide enhanced search capabilities.

Villanova University Villanova, PA

Adjunct Professor of Data Science & Statistics

Aug 2020 - Present

- Build the syllabus, lectures, assignments, projects, and tests for undergraduate Data Science, Intro to Statistics, and Intro to Statistics for Biology
 courses
- Advise and mentor students by writing recommendations for various programs, helping guide studies for real-world success after graduation, and providing assistance through the stresses of university life.

Socure New York, NY

SOLUTIONS CONSULTANT

Jan 2020 - Feb 2021

- Technical expert on fraud prevention, Know Your Customer (KYC)/Customer Identification Program (CIP), Socure product modules, data science, statistics, and data visualization in support of the sales and onboarding processes.
- Created custom proof-of-concept (POC) analyses for prospective customers showing the value of Socure versus their current solution(s).
- Served as the Growth Team's subject matter expert (SME) on data science, creating educational documents and presentations on challenging topics like Area Under the Curve (AUC), false positives, and other model evaluation criteria.
- Worked with the Marketing Team to create content for the Socure Blog on machine learning techniques.

Xfinity Mobile Risk Management (Comcast)

Philadelphia, PA

MANAGER OF DATA ANALYTICS

Mar 2017 - Jan 2020

- Lead and manage the data analytics and engineering team for Xfinity Mobile Credit Risk Management, including hiring and training of staff analysts and engineers, collaborating with and providing analysis for stakeholders, and tracking and prioritizing all team tasking.
- Designed and built a fraud decision making tool that combines custom feature creation, statistical and business rules, and predictive models built in R, Python, and Bash, which, in large part, is responsible for a decrease in month-over-month fraud losses by 92% in 2018.
- · Forecast involuntary churn (both bad debt and unit loss) for the organization on the numerous segments of our customer base.
- Built and maintain numerous Tableau and Splunk dashboards representing fraud and credit to the organization.
- Provide coaching, leadership, and mentorship to all analysts on the Xfinity Mobile Risk Management team.

Philadelphia, PA

SENIOR DATA ANALYST Sep 2014 - Mar 2017

- Designed and built predictive models, which improved compromised user account detection times and discovery accuracy this work was presented internally along with several internal blog posts about the effort.
- Used statistical methods to discover and automate the detection of anomalies.
- Created forecasts of user base growth and project completion.
- Maintained and monitored KPIs for multiple application teams within the organization.

Messaging Application Engineering (Comcast)

Philadelphia, PA

PROJECT MANAGER

Apr 2013 - Sep 2014

- · Served as a Project Manager and ScrumMaster for the Messaging Application Engineering (MAE) team, responsible for Residential Voicemail and Email Engineering teams.
- · Obtained my Project Management Professional (PMP) and Certified ScrumMaster (CSM) certifications.
- · Instituted and evangelized Scrum on both the email and voicemail teams, migrating from a hybrid of waterfall and Kanban, which led to higher team productivity, better communication across teams from development through deployment to production, and improved interaction with our product owners.
- Managed the scheduling and owned the priorities for multiple work streams and teams.

NCS Main Study Information Management Systems Project (Booz Allen Hamilton)

Rockville, MD

IMPLEMENTATION MANAGER

Nov 2010 - Apr 2013

- · Served as the Implementation Manager and Site Administrator for the National Children's Study (NCS) Portal, a Microsoft SharePoint 2010 web application, the NCS Application Homepage, and NCS Password Self Service.
- · Developed a configuration change process for the NCS Portal that streamlined the enhancement process for the site and provided the client with quicker updates while still meeting contractual and firm guidelines.

NAVAIR RIS Project (Booz Allen Hamilton)

Lexington Park, MD

FINANCIAL ANALYST/PROJECT MANAGER

Nov 2009 - Oct 2010

- · Developed a financial tracking system for client, which allowed key stakeholders to view current and projected funding over the lifetime of the
- · Tracked current funding for multiple engineers and monitored the expenditures of funds on their contracts, which ensured that projects remained on budget.

Volunteer.

Data Jawn Conference Philadelphia, PA

ORGANIZER

April 2019 - Present

· Assisted in promotion, speaker selection, and day-of-event logistics for the Data Jawn, a Philadelphia data conference highlighting the great work of our local data commnuity.

Montgomery County Public Defender

Norristown, PA

DATA ANALYST

May 2016 - Jun 2017

- Assisted Montgomery County Public Defender to define an analytics strategy to support competitive salaries and fair defence for all Montgomery County residents.
- · Created, built, and maintained advanced analysis.

Education

Villanova University Villanova, PA

MASTERS OF SCIENCE - APPLIED STATISTICS

2015 - 2017

· Completed my program while working full time

Drexel University Philadelphia, PA

BACHELORS OF SCIENCE - BUSINESS & ENGINEERING

2004 - 2009

- Drexel Representative for Student Lobbying Day in Harrisburg, PA, 2009
- Drexel University Traditions Council Treasurer, 2007 2009
- Dean's List, 2006, 2008
- Drexel Representative to Colonial Athletic Association's Student Athlete Advisory Committee, 2006
- Drexel University Varsity Soccer Player, 2004 2006